Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan and today
we're going to be learning about
the tips and tricks on predicting
and balancing chemical reactions.
Now as you might have started to
realize that in chemistry balancing
reactions can be very very tricky
and especially when you need to
predict them only from your reactants.
But we're going to be going
through some very simple
procedures on how to follow these.
And exactly what it is that we're
going to do in order to solve these.
So stick around and see exactly how it
is that I go through these processes.
This is a practice problem video, so
it's a little bit longer, but we're
going to go through detail on how to do
all these so that way you can do them
on your own for your homework and for
your exams for your chemistry course.
Okay, so thank you so much for
stopping by and let's take a look
at those different tips and tricks.
All right, the first thing that we're
going to have to do is what are our steps?
So the first thing with any chemical
reaction is the beauty of chemi of
general chemistry and introductory chem.
Is that you're following a chemical
recipe like you're reading a cookbook
at home is that you are following this
by the book, meaning that there's only
about five different chemical reactions
that usually you will see you might have
sub labels for them, but they generally
all follow about five different types.
So we're going to look at those.
Uh, the way that this will generally
work is you need to assign each cat ion
and anion or each chemical species a
letter, meaning not like the elemental
symbol, but like your alphabet ABCD.
Um, and this will help you be able
to memorize those different patterns
that you're going to see, right?
Cat patterns are predictable.
Which is crucial to helping
you pass your course.
So these are great things to write
down on a flashcard for yourself, help
you study and to remember them for
your, um, essentially for your course.
When you predict products from scratch,
you need to make sure for step two
is that you swap, drop them if they
are ionic, meaning you need to make
sure that the charges are balanced.
Same thing applies for
covalent species as well.
is you need to make sure that all
of your bonding trends are followed.
So if you still need help on Lewis
structures and to try and do covalent
structures and swap drop, refer to my
other videos, review those concepts
because you don't want those basic skills
to hold you back in these problems.
Then the last step is balancing the
chemical reaction, which we will be going
through some little tricks and tips.
And that as well throughout this video,
let's go take a look at our first, our
look at our chemical recipes that we're
going to be following, and then we're
going to go into our first example.
So when we are looking at our chemical
recipes, meaning our different
chemical reactions that we will see.
Generally, in general chemistry,
you will see five major types.
So what are they?
The first one is a combination
reaction, meaning you will generally
see it as A plus B is equal to AB.
This is going to make more sense
when we go through our examples.
So what we do is we assign
each species a letter.
So we have one, two species
being combined together.
You have decomposition, which
is a B is leading to a plus B.
You have single replacement, which
is a plus B C leads to a C plus
B double this double replacement
or displacement is a B plus CD.
And notice how each swap or each
swap with each other or trade play
trade places, which is a D plus CB.
And then you have our combustion reaction,
which kind of doesn't really follow any
letters, but it does always have the same
products and the same major ingredients
where we have a hydrocarbon combined
with oxygen gas to make CO2 and water.
So these are our five types.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to identify our
reaction to help us predict.
We will go through our swap drop
and then we will go through our
balancing act in order to do these.
So, stick around and let's go through
all those different examples together.
Okay, so in our first reaction
that we are going to be
practicing, we have H2 plus O2 gas.
How exactly are we going to do this?
Well, the general idea is we need to
assign letters to each of our species.
So that way we can determine
which recipe we have.
So on our first element
we have hydrogen, right?
So hydrogen is an element by itself.
So what we are going to do is we
are going to label this the letter A
because it's the only element here.
We don't bother with
anything with the subscripts.
We're just labeling each type of species
we see or each cation, each anion.
Every individual species of
hydrogen gas is our species
here on our next letter, right?
We see that we have oxygen So this is
going to be a B in this case being that
once again, it is by itself So that's
going to be our next species So now what
we're going to look at is trying to figure
out which chemical recipe does that match?
So when we do that receipt with our
first one here is that the combination
reaction is a plus B is equal to a b.
So that's going to be
what we will have here.
So when we are doing this,
we'll write that down for
ourselves is write down our a b.
So we have a and b combined together.
So what we are then going to do
is we're not just going to just
combine everything together.
So you don't want to just write.
H2O2 and you're good.
It's, that is a big, that's a big no.
You don't want to just write that down.
We are going to write each
individual species first.
So we have H as one and then we have O.
Now is that the correct answer?
And it looks really, really
ugly and hideous at the moment.
It's not quite right.
So what we need to do is we
need to either swap drop.
However, both H and O
together is covalent.
So what we need to do is
go off our bonding trends.
If you remember, oxygen makes
two bonds, hydrogen makes one.
So what would we have here is H2O is
going to be our product in this case.
So you're going to make water.
So that would be our
first chemical reaction.
Now the, our last step that
we're going to be doing is
we're going to be balancing it.
So we have H2 and O2
and H2 plus O2 is H2O.
So is it balanced?
Well, let's take a look.
So we look on the left
and the right side here.
We have two oxygens.
That are in two hydrogens
now on the right side.
We have two hydrogens, one oxygen.
So we see there's it's not quite right.
So we will add a two in front of water
to multiply both of the hydrogen, oxygen,
and then we will put a two in front of
hydrogen to balance out the two sides.
See, kind of like zigzag back and forth
is the method I usually kind of revert to.
The C is everything on the two sides.
So we see we have four hydrogens,
two oxygens, everything, it's great.
Let's go on to the next example.
All right, so our next one.
So here again, we have beryllium plus,
uh, hydrofluoric acid adding together.
So what we're going to do right
now is assign our letters.
So our first one, right,
beryllium is all by itself.
So we'll give that the letter A.
Then we have H and F, so that's going
to be, H would be a B in this case,
and then with uh, fluorine would be C.
Um, even though these are covalent,
we could, you could let the letter,
the, the uh, their charges kind
of guide you here if it helps you
see the two different species.
Being that hydrogen is usually a
plus and, and fluorine is a minus,
that is one way to help you see
it, but they are still covalent.
So being that we have A plus
BC, all right, which reaction
are we going to follow?
So we are looking for A plus BC.
And what we see here is right
here in the middle is A plus BC.
So what we're going to
write down is our recipe.
And it says that, okay, A plus
B C is equal to A C plus B.
Alright, so let's follow that.
So now what we are looking
for is what is our A species?
Well, we have beryllium, and if we want
to think of it as being that we have to
swap drop this, we will write the charges.
So we have two plus for beryllium.
Then we have fluorine, which
is a minus one charge, and then
that's going to be plus hydrogen.
Now to keep in mind, we got to
remember is what is the natural way
that hydrogen is created, right?
What's its natural state?
This is one of your seven diatomic gases.
So being that this is a 7, or one of
the diatomic 7, we need to write this
as H2, and if you're not sure what
I'm talking about about those diatomic
gases, refer to my diatomic gas video,
it will help you remember those.
Alright, so, now for step
two, which is swap drop.
We see that with beryllium and
fluorine, it's not balanced charge
wise, they need to be neutral.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to bring the two from beryllium
down and make a BEF2 plus H2, okay,
and then that's going to be a balanced
chemical equation in terms of charge.
So, now the last step is making
sure that, okay, well, are all of
our coefficients, subscripts, is
everything balanced in this problem?
And one thing you're going to
kind of quickly notice is that on
the right hand side we have two
hydrogens, on the left we have one.
It's not quite right.
So what we will do is we'll put
a two on the left, and then that
balances not only the hydrogens.
But it also balances what it's next
to, which is the fluorines as well.
Okay, so it does all of it at one, so
this is our balanced chemical reaction.
Usually the single replacement
ones are really, really easy
to balance most of the time.
Let's predict and balance the
following chemical reaction.
We have calcium hydroxide
reacting with phosphoric acid.
So this is an acid base reaction.
So how can we label this?
Well, just like any,
whenever it's acid base.
You're going to kind of see
the same general trend here.
So what we will do is we will label
all of our cations and anions.
One trick that is really helpful is label
your ions before you swap drop anything.
So realizing calcium is two plus
hydroxide is a polyatomic that's minus.
Hydrogen's a plus,
phosphate's a three minus.
If you label it at the start, it
makes your process a lot easier later.
So keep that in mind.
It also helps you see the letters,
which is also really good, right?
So we have calcium, right?
That's A.
Hydroxide is B.
Then we have our new species over here.
We have hydrogen and then phosphate.
So we see AB plus CD.
So what we are looking for is,
okay, well, what quite matches that?
And we see that this double displacement
reactions will match that recipe here.
So this is going to be our answer.
So A B plus C D is going
to equal to A D plus C B.
So let's write that down for ourselves.
So we have A D plus C B.
All right.
So what is A?
So we will have calcium is
going to be our first one.
So we have calcium two plus that's
going to combine with phosphate.
So we'll use a different color here.
So P O four.
Three minus.
So one thing that you're going to
kind of notice is that, okay, we
have to swap drop these, right?
Cause it's not charge balanced.
So the three is of the charge is
going to come next to calcium.
And then we will put the phosphate in
parentheses and put a two on the outside.
So let's kind of highlight those
in their respective colors so we
can see where those swap dropped.
Okay.
Some classes may also call it a swappy
swappy because we're treating those
two charges now Our next part is C B.
So we have hydrogen which is H
plus and then B is O H Minus.
Alright, so O H minus All right So
this is our first part One thing
you might notice is if you kind of
look over here on the right hand
side H O H What does that exactly?
look like?
Well, when we have H O H written,
it's really handy to write
that to help you balance it.
Um, but when we kind of
summarize it later, it's going
to be written as H 2 O, right?
Cause that's what it actually is.
So, but I'm going to leave it like
that to show you a balancing trick.
One of the things that students, whenever
they see polyatomic, uh, problems, they
always kind of freak out a little bit
because they do look like one of the most
complicated problems that you can possibly
see, but there is a hidden trick behind
them that makes them extremely easy to do.
And that is the fact that the polyatomics
are on both sides of the equation.
So I just highlighted them
in their respective colors.
So you see hydroxide is in purple,
and then you have phosphate, which
is in red, and it's on both the
left and the right hand side of the
equation, which is Really, really nice.
So what we are going to use
to balance this is what I
refer to as the zigzag method.
I don't know if anyone's
actually, if anyone's named this
one, but this is how I name it.
And it's all about going
back and forth to balance.
With the zigzag method, what we're going
to first start with is we're going to
start with the phosphates in this case.
So what we see here is on the
right hand side, we have two
phosphates in our formula.
So we got two right here and
we only have one on the left.
So what we are going to do is put
a two in front of the less species.
So what we now have is two phosphates
and what we will then do is zigzag
to the hydrogens and look at them.
So we have six hydrogens on the
left, and one thing you'll notice is
that we have only one hydrogen, even
though there's an OH here, separate
them, they're going to be separate.
So what we will do is put a six in
front of our hydrogen to balance them.
We'll then zigzag it
to its partner, right?
So we're always kind of going
back and forth, back and forth.
We have six hydroxides now, and we will
look on the other side of the equation
where we only have two hydroxides.
So we'll put a three over here
to make them both equal to six.
So we have three times two on
the left hand side of hydroxide.
We'll then zigzag to its partner.
So we have three calciums, and if
one thing you will notice over here
is we already have three calciums.
So it balanced it.
The problem balances itself when
you go forth, back and forth.
So when we did this, right, just to
kind of number it and to review it real
quick, we first did the phosphates.
We then went to the hydrogens and then
we did the hydroxides and the calciums.
Okay.
So we went from one, two, three, when
we did this, it makes it a lot easier.
You don't have to write a list.
And it makes it a little bit more
enjoyable when you're doing the problem.
Let's go on to our next one.
All right, let's predict and balance
the following chemical reaction again.
So we have aluminum plus oxygen gas.
So what we can see here is we have
aluminum, which is a, then we have
oxygen, which is going to be B.
So we have a plus B and
we've seen this one before.
So a plus B is combination.
So what we are going to be doing is
following the first reaction in this list.
So A plus B is combined
together to make AB.
So here we have what's going to
occur is this is going to be an
oxidation reduction reaction.
So this one we will write
as we will write the ions.
We have aluminum, which has a charge
of three plus, and we have oxygen,
which has a charge of two minus.
And what we are going to do is swap the
numbers to each side, so the 3 is going
to come down, and then the 2 is going
to come down, just like so, and we can
kind of clean up our little arrows.
So we are moving all those
little pieces around, and then
this will be our final product.
Now what we need to do is,
once again, is balance it.
So the, once again, you can kind
of use the zigzag method mainly
applies to double displacement, but
it is usable for single as well.
One of the things that I always
try to keep in mind too, is if
you have species by themselves.
So notice how we have
aluminum by itself, oxygen.
If you have a really complicated
problem, leave them for last to
balance because it's only going to
make your life a little bit easier.
So leave lonely elements.
The other tip I would really recommend
as well is you want to even the odds.
So one thing here is that you're
going to notice is that I have three
oxygens on the right, two on the left.
So what you want to do is find what the
least common multiple of the two are.
So three times two is six.
Which will make it an even number so if
I were to do that right even the odds
I have a total of six oxygens on the
left six oxygens on the right therefore
Making it even right and which is one of
the ultimate goals Now, by doing so, you
can now see I have four aluminums on the
right hand side, so what I need to do is
by saving the lonely element for last, we
can now add a four easily in front of our
aluminum that's by itself, and it doesn't
affect any other elements, which is great.
It's fantastic.
It makes it really, really easy.
So these are two tips I would
recommend writing them down.
They've helped me many times
doing tons of reactions.
Let's go on to our next one.
Let's predict and balance
the following reactions.
So we have propane gas and it's going
to be combining with oxygen gas.
So C3H8 is propane.
So just like what you use for grilling.
So with this one, one thing that this is a
very unique chemical compound, and you're
going to notice is that it's going to
follow the combustion reaction down here.
So notice how this is what
I consider CxHy, x and y are
just any number subscript.
So what this thing is
called is a hydrocarbon.
Being that it's made of hydrogen
and carbon, so it's what we burn.
So, this guy, what it's always
going to do is going to follow
the exact same recipe every time.
In order for fire to breathe, it
needs oxygen for that to happen.
If there's no oxygen, the fire goes out.
So, you're always going to make CO2.
and water when we have
a complete combustion.
So we're going to write those down.
So when we are doing these,
there's a couple little tricks
that you want to keep in mind.
I always recommend start with carbon.
Okay, and the other thing to keep in
mind is don't be afraid to double your
hydrogen hydrocarbon if you need it to.
So it depends on kind of, uh, it
depends on how complicated it is.
The bigger it is, the likely you might
have to put a two in front of it.
So it's an easy trick to kind of keep in
mind, but sometimes you might need to,
um, it just, it just comes with practice.
So we have our carbons, what
we're going to start with.
So, we have three carbons on the left hand
side, we have one on the right, so we are
going to put a three in front of carbon.
So what we can see is
carbons are now balanced.
The second thing you want to start with is
go to start with hydrogen, because if you
remember my rule from last time is leave
the lonely elements for last, next, okay,
so leave them for last, which is that O2.
is by itself.
So you want to make sure that you kind
of, you leave it for the last thing.
Okay.
So second hydrogen.
So what we have on the left hand side
is we have Oh, eight hydrogens, so
we need to have eight on the right.
So what we are going to do is
balance that by putting a four
in front of this hydrogen.
So what we now have is eight hydrogens,
eight hydrogens were balanced there.
Oxygens are tricky.
This is where you're going to
know if you need to double your
hydrocarbon or not, because oxygen is
coming from three different places.
So one thing you're going to
notice is we have three or sorry,
not three different plates come
with two places on the product.
So we have three times two and then
four times one on the right hand side.
So you have six plus four.
So there's 10 oxygens.
If this number is odd, then you
need to double your hydrocarbon.
If it is even, you're fine.
You don't need to go any farther.
So it's even in this case.
So what we need to do is put
a 5 in front of our O2 to make
total 10 carbons on the left.
We now have a balanced combustion problem.
So if oxygen is odd, you will have
to double your hydrocarbon by putting
a 2 in front of Let's predict and
balance the following problem.
So we have MgCO3 and it says that
it's going to be heated and it's
going to yield this following product.
So whenever we have the triangle that's
above our arrow, that's referring to heat.
So all of our favorite using
heat and thermochemistry.
So when this occurs, so
how, what are we looking at?
Well, we have Mg, right?
If you can remember, that's
one of our ionic species.
So that's going to be 2 Then carbonate,
which is a polyatomic, is 2 So that
means you are going to have A and
B as your two different species.
So one thing that we might be able to,
you might be able to see is that for
decomposition, it's A B leads to A plus B.
So we're going to be following
this second reaction.
So we're going to be making A and B.
Now, one thing about these is
you need to kind of be careful
how you are separating them.
It depends on really
what compound you have.
Sometimes it doesn't separate evenly.
It depends on the structure.
So CO three is a very common gas
evolution product, and this is
in another video of mine where
it goes over the four major ones.
So if you ever see a carbonate, you
have to be aware that most likely
one of the products gonna be CO2.
And the reason for it actually
has to do with its structure here.
So I have MgCO3 here, so this is what
I showed earlier, so Mg and then CO3,
and what's going to happen when this
guy gets heated up and decomposes.
Is the molecule is going to separate
into its two pieces, just like this.
It's, and what we're going to have
is it's going to rearrange itself
into its linear geometry for CO2.
And then we'll have MgO on the right.
So when we write this, we have MgO.
And one thing you'll notice is that
it's 2 plus, 2 minus, so it's actually
very happy in terms of charges.
And then the other species is CO2.
So it's no longer ionic.
It's, or sorry, it's not like
the part is ionic species.
It's now a covalent gas.
So as it's changing, so not only
do we have a solid that's forming,
but we also have a gas that's being
generated in the problem as well.
Which is kind of pretty cool.
Now, the biggest thing about these
is just making sure everything's swap
dropped okay, um, and it's actually
already balanced, so we don't have to
do anything at all with this particular
reaction, which is very, very nice for us.
So, this is the big thing when
we're looking at all these.
So, when you are predicting and trying all
these different things, try to remember
some of these little tips and tricks.
And to keep in mind is follow your recipe,
swap drop when needed, balance your
chemical reaction, and you will be fine.
The big issue though, if you are still
watching this, for anyone that's watching
on YouTube or in class, you need to
practice your chemical reactions as much
as possible in order to get comfortable
with swap dropping, with balancing,
with ionic naming, with balancing.
It brings together all of your skills
you've learned until this point.
And it can be overwhelming at first,
but if you keep practicing, do
optional problems in your textbook,
do problems in your homework, you
will master it and overcome it.
You can do this.
I believe in you.
And if you need any extra help,
please comment below and let me know.
Uh, and please, please hit that like and
subscribe button if you're just a viewer
and thank you all so much for watching.
All right.
I will see y'all later.